[Legend of the Magnate]
[Episode 12]
I almost forgot you're a princess.
I wanted to give you a gift.
I've been thinking about it,
but couldn't decide what to pick.
So I'll give
Miss Bai, whom I've never met,
a small gift.
No need for that.
I'm afraid I might not
make it to your wedding.
So giving it early
can put my mind at ease.
But I realized
that with you by her side,
she's already
got the whole world.
So what else could I even give her?
Take it.
Your safety is
the best gift I can give her.
This is His Highness's gift for you.
I can't accept it.
What use is it to me?
My father was imprisoned,
and I almost got killed as well.
Could this possibly save me?
But you can keep it
and occasionally recall
the title of "princess"
just for fun.
I
won't keep any more.
Will you continue to help Mr. Chang
with the horse gang?
Of course.
We stick to our own world.
Then you
take care on your journey.
Gu.
This past year,
I've been reading some books.
Father and I have been
on the move everywhere since I was little,
but I never learned
to speak like a scholar.
That doesn't matter.
The chivalrous are often the humble,
while the heartless are often scholars.
That's the fault of the heartless person,
not the books.
I read in books
that when scholars bid farewell,
they always compose and exchange poems.
Let me recite a poem
I read this morning to send you off.
"Gloomy winds and rain;
roosters crow without cease.
Having met you, my dear.
I couldn't rejoice more."
♪ Names being etched
and centered in the time ♪
♪ A goose flying across the barren plains,
carrying the setting sun's last light ♪
Gu.
Take care.
♪ An old friend suddenly comes to mind,
and the world feels vast and desolate ♪
♪ Here, I dreamed of you ♪
♪ The candlelight casts the glow on me ♪
♪ The rain soaks the paper umbrella;
the red mark on my sleeve spreads ♪
♪ Ride home on horseback ♪
♪ The wind brushes past the old eaves
on a cool night ♪
♪ Look, the lanterns sway and cast shadow
of our overlapping silhouettes ♪
♪ Forget about how long the path is ♪
Are you an official or a soldier?
♪ This is etched into my soul,
unforgettable for life ♪
I am a convict.
You're a good person.
May heaven bless you.
You'll get to the bottom of this.
♪ Names being etched
and centered in the time ♪
You won't stay wrongly accused
your whole life without answers.
If I beg your father
♪ A goose flying across the barren plains,
carrying the setting sun's last light ♪
to take me as his student
and teach me about business...
If he won't teach you,
I can!
♪ The rain soaks the paper umbrella;
the red mark on my sleeve spreads ♪
Gu.
♪ My heart races so fast
like a surging sea ♪
Our lives are
tied together.
♪ Longing sweeps through like starlight ♪
♪ Even when hair turns grey, we'll still
gaze at each other, fingers entwined ♪
♪ The Milky Way spans the west window ♪
Everyone.
My home is just up ahead.
Come with me to the village.
Your Highness,
we were ordered
to escort you only this far.
From here on, you'll walk
the rest of the path yourself.
Farewell.
How could that be?
You've worked hard escorting me
all this way.
You must at least come with me for a meal.
We're bound by military orders
that we dare not disobey.
Your Highness, please say no more.
Someday,
when you and the Princess
return to Horqin,
I will serve you drinks again.
Let's go.
[Shanjian Village, Huizhou]
[Gu's Mansion]
Mother.
[Mrs. Gu, Mother of Gu Pingyuan]
I'm Pingyuan.
Your son.
I, your son, am back.
Mother!
Pingyuan!
Is it really you?
My son is back!
You are my firstborn son.
Pingyuan.
God is merciful.
God showed mercy!
God let us, mother and son,
reunite while still alive!
Pingyuan, let me look at you.
My son,
I've nearly cried my eyes blind.
My son.
I've been waiting...
I've been waiting for your return.
My son.
We've literally had the worst luck.
What kind of world is this?
It's always the common people who suffer.
What...
Pingwen.
You've grown taller.
[Gu Pingwen, the Gu Family's Second Son]
Don't you recognize me?
Get up.
Brother.
Now you know I'm your brother?
You hit way too hard!
You've finally come back!
We thought
you were dead all these years!
I had to do
all the work by myself.
[Gu's Mansion]
Mother's eyes are like this
because she's cried too much
and too frequently.
Now that you're back,
she'll surely get better day by day.
I remember
that when you were just taken away,
I always saw Mother crying.
Back then, Mr. Bai
would occasionally come
to talk with Mother.
Later, he had difficulty walking
and stopped coming.
I still had to work in the fields
while there was no one
to keep Mother company at home.
I'm not a child.
Why would I need company?
Even if I go completely blind,
I can still spin thread.
That's true.
Despite Mother's poor eyesight,
the thread she spins is
so fine and delicate
that even young girls can't make it.
What about Mr. Bai?
Besides his leg problem,
what else is wrong with him?
His legs have a problem,
and his temper is even worse.
He always yells at people
like me.
I'll take you to see him tomorrow.
But I'm not going in.
I don't want to be scolded again.
His bad temper isn't
anything new.
I remember when I was little,
if I couldn't recite the articles,
he would hit my palms,
making my hands swell.
If I have to name someone
in this world
who makes my legs tremble
just by seeing them,
it would definitely be Mr. Bai.
You got off easy.
Back in my day,
he hit my hands
and twisted my ears,
which ended up like Buddha's long ears.
That was what you get
for not studying hard.
If you were like me,
reciting articles well,
you could even stay
for dinner at his house.
If I had Miss Bai
studying with me,
I would have done better than you.
Well,
how is Yimei doing?
Has she
gotten married already?
No.
I know.
I made her
wait for me all these years.
She's suffered.
So,
first thing tomorrow morning,
I'll go visit Mr. Bai
and apologize to him in person.
Whether he beats me up
or scolds me,
at least it makes me feel better inside.
By the way,
on my way back,
I saw some burned tea plants
in the tea plantation.
What happened?
Tell him.
Otherwise, your brother
won't eat
or sleep well.
Last month,
soldiers fought a battle here.
So the tea plantation was burned.
Qimen was besieged, too.
And Miss Bai was taken away
by the southern army.
In the whole village,
except for little girls and elderly women,
all women who could work were
taken away.
They said
it was to look after wounded soldiers
and do laundry.
They promised to release them in 10 days,
but it's been a month now.
These days,
people in the village are saying
that we should select someone
to go demand their return.
But we can't get in.
We would be driven away at the gate.
They have all kinds of weapons,
like swords, guns, spears, and axes.
Are we throwing ourselves at them?
Do you know which army it is?
It's said to be
the Resistance Army from Guangxi.
They're led by a general surnamed Li.
He's quite formidable.
They're even planning to attack Hefei.
So, when is our village
planning to ask for our people back?
I already told you.
We can't get through the camp entrance.
Who would dare to force their way in?
No one dares.
Yimei has been captured.
Then Mr. Bai...
Pingyuan,
you should go see him tomorrow.
All these years, it's been Pingwen
delivering firewood and water
to their home.
Yimei's life hanging by a thread,
Mr. Bai must be
as worried as I used to be.
Mother,
don't think too much.
Let's enjoy our meal.
Now that I'm back,
I won't be away for so long again.
This war will eventually
come to an end one day.
And I think that day will soon come.
Once the war is over,
Pingwen and I will
fix up the tea plantation.
We'll continue selling our tea,
run our business well,
and live a good life.
Mother,
don't worry too much.
Your health comes first.
Our good days are yet to come.
Don't fall ill or get into trouble.
I once heard
these words in my dreams.
Now I can hear you say them in person.
Even if I were to die right now,
it would be worth it.
Pingyuan,
I don't remember seeing you
carry a shoulder pole before.
You're doing pretty well.
I used to think of myself as a scholar.
Why would I need to carry firewood?
But later in Ningguta,
I hunted tigers in the mountains
and panned for gold in the rivers.
Carrying a shoulder pole?
That's a piece of cake.
Mr. Bai,
I, Pingwen, am here
to bring you water and firewood.
Carrying water and delivering firewood are
two jobs.
What do you mean
by "bring you water and firewood"?
Do you have multiple heads and arms?
Did you hear that, Pingyuan?
How nitpicky he is.
This isn't nitpicking.
Incorrect names lead to discrepancies
between words and truths.
And with these discrepancies,
things won't make sense.
If things won't make sense,
nothing can be accomplished.
Didn't I teach you this
when you were a student?
Mr. Bai,
I-I'll be going now.
Mr. Bai.
[Bai Shi'an, Private School Teacher]
I'm your student, Gu Pingyuan.
I'm back
to greet you.
P-Pingyuan, you're back?
Pingyuan!
You rascal.
You little rascal.
I...
You made us worried sick about you.
Do you know that?
Good.
Come on.
Get up now.
Get up quickly.
Alright, let's...
L-Let's go inside
to have a nice chat.
Come inside quickly.
[A long journey
with heavy responsibilities]
Come on in.
Mr. Bai,
your place hasn't changed at all.
That's great.
What's so good about it?
I remember back then,
seeing that I was too small,
you let me sit in the front.
Right here.
At that time, my feet
couldn't even touch the ground.
You squatted
by my wall to eavesdrop every day,
fell asleep halfway through,
and even snored.
I kept wondering
if my teaching was really that boring.
The sunshine was so comfortable back then.
Once I basked in the sun,
I'd fall asleep in no time.
Did you come back yesterday?
My mother told me that you've been
having trouble with your legs.
She asked Pingwen and me
to come visit you early this morning.
Is your mother feeling better?
Last night, when she saw me
and we talked for a while,
her eyes seemed to light up a bit.
I've failed to be
a good son all these years.
Someone set you up
in the examination site.
Guess it was a tribulation
you were destined to suffer.
Being back today is
a blessing in and of itself.
Mr. Bai,
please don't sigh.
I heard
that Yimei was taken away, right?
All the women in the village
have been taken away.
I think they're probably
being made to do sewing and washing work.
Isn't the village just
looking for a representative
to go to the camp
and ask for their return?
I think I can go.
A scholar can't talk sense
into soldiers.
Don't go.
We should choose a smooth talker.
Mr. Bai,
I'm no longer a scholar.
My academic title was revoked.
Now I've got a way
with words.
Trust me.
These past few years,
you've indeed grown a lot.
Once I bring Yimei back,
I'll marry her right away.
Last night with my mother,
I said these words.
Today, facing you, Mr. Bai,
I say the same thing.
Mr. Bai,
you must take good care of yourself.
I still need to take good care of you
as my father-in-law.
If this comes true,
I'd be such a lucky man
in my twilight years!
I have a good student,
an excellent son-in-law,
to bring me joy by my side.
How wonderful.
What a joy.
Pingwen.
Is there any place nearby
that sells hemp ropes?
Hemp ropes? We have some at home.
No, I mean the big kind.
In large bundles. The thick type.
Those villages down there all grow hemp.
You could go look for them.
How much do you want to buy?
About 400 or 500 taels worth.
400 or 500 taels?
That's about several warehouses of hemp!
Exactly.
Is that possible?
Stop bragging, okay?
Even if you have people
from several villages
twist ropes with you
for three years,
you still can't make
ropes worth 400 or 500 taels.
A quick question for you.
Would you like to learn
to do business from me?
I'd like to.
But I only know how to grow tea.
Well then,
from now on,
I'll be your teacher.
Observe carefully when you're with me,
listen closely,
and ask me privately
about anything you don't get.
Remember,
never question
any of my decisions in front of others.
Alright. Have a safe trip, sir.
These are the last two baskets.
How do I look?
Why did you grab
Li's glasses?
I paid!
They'll come in handy.
Let's go
sell hemp ropes.
[The Military Camp of Li Cheng,
Resistance Army]
Stop there!
Where do you think you're trespassing?
Go back!
Go back?
What about my cartload of goods?
Take your things and get lost.
No outsiders are allowed
into the military camp.
Don't you know that?
Young man,
may I have your name?
So when Li Cheng asks me about it,
I can tell him
who drove me away.
If you don't make yourself clear,
how can we let you in?
Our general's orders are
very strict.
Let me tell you.
This cartload of goods is urgent supplies
for your naval forces,
not easy to get these days.
Not letting me in, right?
Fine, we're leaving.
Wait, wait, wait!
Was it really the General
who asked you to come?
Come on, get up here.
I'll take you inside.
You can ask him yourself, alright?
You may go in by yourself.
Listen,
once you enter the camp,
you must get off the wagon
and don't park anywhere.
All forms of driving
and horseback riding are
prohibited in the camp.
Pay attention to this.
Yes, sir.
Come on,
clear the way!
There are two people outside
asking to meet the General.
It's these two, right?
Yes.
You may go.
You're the one
looking for our general, huh?
General Li is busy with work.
Just leave these things
over there and go.
I'll report it to him later.
Go and report
that his cousin,
Gu Pingyuan, is here.
How impertinent!
No matter how busy he is,
how can he not meet me?
Cousin?
So you claim to be
our general's cousin, right?
Go report to him now!
Alright.
How about this?
You go by yourselves.
See that gate ahead?
Go through it
and then go straight.
The large tent up front is
our general's headquarters.
Go ahead.
Off you go.
Take it slow in there.
Go ahead.
Li
leads his troops quite well.
How do you know about leading troops?
Back when I was in Ningguta,
I hung around with the soldiers there
and learned a bit.
I think you've
picked up other skills, too.
What?
Your smooth talk and lies.
How could you be
Li Cheng's cousin?
What will you say
when you meet him later?
I'm just playing it by ear.
How else would we get in without bluffing?
Is General Li Cheng inside?
I, Gu Pingyuan, am seeking an audience.
You bluffer.
Cousin?
Take them away.
Do we really
have to besiege Hefei?
The imperial court's army
has already pulled through
the toughest time.
The navy controls
the middle and upper reaches.
Now we still have a chance
to push northward.
If we spend
too much time in Hefei,
it will bring us big trouble!
Do you still remember
the last northern campaign?
Say no more.
We'll follow orders from above.
I'm afraid he only cares
about his Sufu Province
and ignores Tianjing.
Ever since His Lordship passed away,
something feels off.
Forgive me for saying this,
but our situation is deteriorating
day by day.
General,
there's no point
in our staying in Huizhou.
They want us to create a diversion
to support the navy.
With these few troops,
how can we pull it off?
Besides, given Huizhou's low terrain,
we're here just for the imperial court
to have its troops raid us.
With insufficient forces,
a long defense line,
and frequent night attacks from the enemy,
all camps are rattled
in a state of low morale.
Everyone,
you're all my old pals
from Guangxi.
I've joined
the Resistance Army since childhood,
rising from a child soldier to a general.
I clearly remember
that we all swore
to overthrow the Qing Dynasty.
Since we followed the Heavenly King,
kept our hair, and rose up,
we should know
that this is a war to the death
with no turning back.
Alright,
return to your camps
and stabilize the morale.
Furthermore,
don't let me hear of anyone
plundering villages again.
Otherwise,
I'll execute them before reporting
with no mercy.
Yes, General.
Who is that general?
You've claimed to be
my general's cousin for a while.
And you don't even know who he is?
General Li!
How stupid you are.
Swaggering into our camp so boldly,
you truly have no regard
for those heroic figures.
I'm just a small merchant.
To seek profits,
I played a trick and accidentally
entered your camp.
Please forgive me, General.
A small merchant?
You're lying!
Who on earth are you?
Where's my brother?
Your brother?
Your brother is dead because of you.
Your brother...
General Li, you lead the army
in a disciplined way,
and you don't look like someone
who kills innocents.
I just want to make a deal with you.
Will you let me up, please?
Make a deal?
[Li Cheng, General of the Resistance Army]
What deal?
Did you see
my cart full of hemp ropes?
I know your navy
needs a large quantity of hemp ropes
to reinforce the ships.
People in Huizhou
dare not sell any to you.
I can help you purchase what you need.
Does he look like
a spy sent by the imperial court?
Yes, he does.
No, I don't.
I...
About 25 kilometers from here,
there's Shanjian Village.
You took
all the women here
from that village,
saying that you would
return them in 10 days.
It's been a month now,
and there's been no news at all.
I'm from that village.
What's your name?
My name is Gu Pingyuan.
I've lived in Shanjian Village
since childhood.
I have a teacher surnamed Bai.
His daughter is called Bai Yimei.
"Mei" as in plum blossom.
She should be in your military camp now.
You can ask her
about me.
Continue with the hemp ropes.
I know you need
a whole lot of hemp ropes.
The people in the village might
not be enough.
All these women can twist ropes.
Letting them back
can work in your favor, too.
I have so many wounded soldiers.
Who will take care of them
if the women leave?
General,
forgive me for being blunt.
You won't be able
to stay here much longer.
Those women are innocent.
I don't want them to die here.
Who told you
that I won't be staying here long?
You've been besieging Hefei
for over 2 months.
Yet you still haven't taken it.
Once the imperial court's troops arrive,
they'll surround you completely.
Watch what you're saying!
General Li,
I just have one question.
Have you already killed
those women who were brought here?
If so,
just give me a straight answer.
So I can go back to the village
with the news.
Untie his feet.
Bring him out.
Yes, General.
Come on.
Open the door.
See?
In our Resistance Army,
we have separate camps for men and women.
Even married couples
must sleep separately.
We lead our troops differently
from those brutal guys.
For the poor things in the world,
we treat men like our brothers
and women like our sisters.
Our Resistance Army
will never mistreat them.
See clearly now?
If you do, then just leave.
Get these two brothers
out of the camp.
Understood.
Go.
Go!
Night raid!
Form ranks for battle!
Charge!
Kill them!
Yimei.
Yimei!
Gu!
Yimei.
It really is you.
Did you get hurt?
[Bai Yimei, Daughter of Bai Shi'an]
Where are the other women
from our village?
They scattered when the firing started.
Quickly, come with me.
No.
These two were wounded by arrows.
They need water every few minutes.
At a time like this, you still...
Then help me first.
Move aside!
Get out of the way!
Move!
Fire!
Pingwen?
Save me!
Help! Help me!
Help!
It's on fire!
Untie them all.
I'll go find the other women.
Okay.
Help me!
I'll help you one by one.
Anyone from Shanjian Village?
Is there anyone from Shanjian Village?
Those from Shanjian Village, follow me!
Anyone from Shanjian Village?
Pingyuan!
Pingyuan.
Pingwen.
Yimei is still in the hut.
Let's hurry inside!
Okay.
Yimei!
No time to waste!
Let's run.
Be careful.
Fall back!
Go back!
Back off!
Fall back!
-Back off!
-Go back!
Fall back!
You!
Get back!
Pingyuan! Pingyuan! Pingyuan!
Gu!
Let me go!
Let go of me!
What are you waiting for?
There must be a snitch among them!
The General is injured.
Check every one of them!
Si,
go check on the medic now.
I can help.
I know how to treat patients! Let me help!
Don't hurt anyone!
Stop!
Who just spoke?
Me.
It was me.
I beg you.
P-Please don't hurt anyone.
I-I've studied medicine since childhood.
I...